l.sharrock@lancaster.ac.uk | https://louissharrock.github.io/

School of Mathematics University of Bristol Fry Building, Woodland Road Bristol, BS8 1UG

SUMMARY

Senior Research Associate in Statistical Machine Learning at Lancaster University. Previously HIMR Data Science Research Fellow at the University of Bristol. PhD in Statistics from Imperial College London, and MA in Mathematics from the University of Cambridge.

Research interests include machine learning, optimisation, and computational statistics, with a particular focus on likelihood-free inference and stochastic gradient MCMC. Current research focuses on the development of new algorithms for high dimensional Bayesian inference, score-based methods for likelihood-free inference, and online parameter estimation for mean-field equations.

RESEARCH EMPLOYMENT

2022 - Present Senior Research Associate in Statistical Machine Learning

Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Lancaster University

2022 - Present Research Consultant

Heilbronn Institute for Mathematical Research

2022 - Present Honorary Senior Research Associate

School of Mathematics, University of Bristol

2022 Heilbronn Data Science Research Fellow

Department of Mathematics, University of Bristol

EDUCATION

2018 - 2022 PhD in Statistics

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "On the Theory and Applications of Stochastic Gradient Descent in

Continuous Time."

2017 - 2018 MRes in Mathematics (Distinction - 93%)

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring."

(91%)

Supervisor: Dr Nikolas Kantas.

2016 - 2017 MSc in Statistics (Distinction - 80%)

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "An Application of Bayesian Networks to Yield Prediction in Bayesian

Viticulture." (91%)

Supervisor: Dr Ben Calderhead.

2013 - 2016 MA (Hons) in Mathematics (2.1)

Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge

CATAM Computational Project: 98% (2nd year), 95% (3rd year).

PUBLICATION	ONS
2023	L. Sharrock , D. Dodd, C. Nemeth (2023). "CoinEM: Tuning-Free Particle-Based Variational Inference For Latent Variable Models." <i>In Review</i> . https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14916.
2023	L. Sharrock , L. Mackey, C. Nemeth (2023). "Learning Rate Free Bayesian Inference in Constrained Domains." <i>In Review</i> . https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.14943.
2023	L. Sharrock, C. Nemeth (2023). "Coin Sampling: Gradient-Based Bayesian Inference without Learning Rates." Proceedings of the 40th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2023), Hawaii. https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.11294.
2023	L. Sharrock, N. Kantas., P. Parpas, and G.A. Pavliotis (2021). "Online Parameter Estimation for the Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Equation." Stochastic Process and their Applications (In Press). https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.13751.
2023	L. Sharrock and N. Kantas (2023). "Two Timescale Stochastic Gradient Descent in Continuous Time with Applications to Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement." <i>Bernoulli</i> , 29(2), 1137-1165. https://doi.org/10.3150/22-BEJ1493.
2022	L. Sharrock (2022). "Two-Timescale Stochastic Approximation for Bilevel Optimisation Problems in Continuous-Time Models." Proceedings of the 39th International Conference for Machine Learning (ICML) Workshop on Continuous-Time Methods for Machine Learning.
2022	L. Sharrock and N. Kantas (2022). "Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement for the Partially Observed Stochastic Advection-Diffusion Equation." SIAM / ASA Journal on Uncertainty Quantification, 10(1), 55-95. https://doi.org/10.1137/20M1375073.
2021	C. Leadbeater*, L. Sharrock* , B. Coyle, and M. Benedetti (2021). "F-Divergences and Cost Function Locality in Generative Modelling with Quantum Circuits." <i>Entropy</i> , 23(10), 1281-1304. https://doi.org/10.3390/e23101281.
In Submission	1
2023	J. Simon, L. Sharrock*, S. Liu, M. Beaumont (2023). "Neural Score Estimation: Likelihood Free Inference with Conditional Score Based Diffusions." In submission to the 5th Symposium on Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference (AABI).
2023	L. Sharrock , J. Simons, S. Liu, M. Beaumont (2022). "Sequential Neural Score Estimation: Likelihood-Free Inference with Conditional Score Based Diffusions." arXiv preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.04872.

2023 L. Sharrock, N. Kantas., P. Parpas, and G.A. Pavliotis (2023) . "Online Learning in McKean-Vlasov SDEs and Interacting Particle Systems using Single Trajectory Data." In preparation.

^{*} denotes joint first authorship.

PRESENTATIONS

Jun 2023	Invited Talk "Mirrors and Coins: Learning-Rate Free Methods for Bayesian Inference in Constrained Domains", OxCSML Seminar, Oxford University (Oxford, UK).
Jun 2023	Invited Talk "Online Learning in McKean-Vlasov SDEs and Interacting Particle Systems using Single Trajectory Data", Stochastic Analysis and Algorithm Seminar, Wuhan University (Online).
Mar 2023	Invited Talk "Coin Sampling: Gradient-Based Bayesian Inference without Learning Rates", BayesComp 2023 (Levi, Finland).
Feb 2023	Invited Talk, "Particle Based Methods for Online ParameterEstimation in McKean-Vlasov Stochastic Differential Equations", SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering (Amsterdam, The Netherlands).
Mar 2022	Invited Talk, "Parameter Estimation for the McKean Stochastic Differential Equation", Computational Statistics and Machine Learning Seminars, Lancaster University (Lancaster, UK).
Mar 2022	Invited Talk, "Parameter Estimation for Weakly Interacting Particle Systems and Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Processes", Statistics Seminars, University of Bristol (Bristol, UK).
Aug 2021	Contributed Talk, "Parameter Estimation for Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Equations", Joint Statistical Meetings 2021 (Virtual).
Jul 2021	Contributed Talk, "Parameter Estimation for Weakly Interacting Particle Systems and Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Processes", Bernoulli-IMS 10th World Congress in Probability and Statistics (Virtual).
Jun 2020	Contributed Talk, "Two Timescale Stochastic Gradient Descent in Continuous Time with Applications to Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement", Mathematics of Data Science Conference (Virtual)
Nov 2019	Contributed Talk, Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring, MATHMET 2019 International Conference (Lisbon, Portugal).
Nov 2019	Contributed Talk, "Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement with Applications to a Stochastic Advection Diffusion Equation", Conference on Big Data, Data Assimilation and Uncertainty Quantification, CliMathParis 2019 (Institut Henri Poincaré, Paris, France).
Nov 2019	Poster Presentation , "Large Scale Inference and Optimal Design with Applications to Environmental Monitoring", <i>The Postgraduate Institute Conference</i> (National Physical Laboratory, Teddington, UK).
Jul 2019	Poster Presentation, "Online Parameter Estimation in Continuous Time with Applications to a Stochastic Advection Diffusion Equation", Workshop on Stochastic Parameterisations and Their Use in Data Assimilation (Imperial College London, London, UK).
May 2019	Poster Presentation, "Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring", Postgraduate Forum (Imperial College London, London, UK).
Nov 2018	Contributed Talk, "An Application of Bayesian Networks to Yield Prediction in Portuguese Viticulture", 6th Annual BayesiaLab Conference (Chicago, USA).

PRIZES AND AWARDS

2023	Yael Dowker Prize (runner-up). Department of Mathematics, Imperial
	College London. A prize awarded for the best Maths PhD Thesis.
2020	Doris Chen Merit Award (shortlisted). Department of Mathematics, Imperial
	College London. A prize awarded to recognise exceptional early promise,
	progress and achievement in PhD studies.
2019	Best Poster Prize, Statistics Section, Postgraduate Forum. Department of
	Mathematics, Imperial College London.
2018	MRes Student of The Year. Centre for Doctoral Training, Mathematics of
	Planet Earth, Imperial College London. A prize awarded to the best overall
	student on the course.
2013 - 2016	BP STEM Scholarship. University of Cambridge. A national scholarship of
	£5000/annum, awarded to ten STEM students each year.
2013	Rowley Mainhood Award. Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge. An
	award recognising outstanding achievement in pre-admission examinations.

Research Funding	
2021	Doris Chen Mobility Fund. Department of Mathematics, Imperial College
	London. A fund providing travel and subsistence for a PhD student with
	exceptional potential to take their research to another university abroad.
2018	CliMathParis Travel Grant. Institut Henri Poincaré. A grant to fund attendance
	at the CliMathParis 2019 conference on big data, data assimilation, and
	uncertainty quantification.
2017	Warner Prize. Statistics Section, Department of Mathematics, Imperial
	College London. A prize awarded to support a talented MSc statistics student
	further develop their research project.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Tooching

reaching	
2023	Instructor, School of Mathematics, University of Bristol
	- Designed and lectured a new unit on statistical machine learning for third year
	undergraduates.
	- Responsibilities included writing and delivering lectures, supervising computer
	labs, writing and marking coursework and exams.

2014 - present Mathematics Tutor, Online (MyTutor)

- Deliver one-to-one tutorials to secondary school, undergraduate, and postgraduate students. Over 850 hours of lessons, 175 five-star reviews.
- Awarded 'premium tutor' status to reflect 'impressive expertise and experience'

2018 - 2021 Graduate Teaching Assistant, Imperial College London

- Supported teaching of undergraduate and postgraduate courses in probability, statistics and machine learning, including group tutorials and lecturing.
- Courses included Data and Uncertainty (postgraduate), Computational Statistics (postgraduate), Probability and Statistics (undergraduate)

2014 - 2015 Mathematics Teaching Assistant, STIMULUS.

- Volunteered as a mathematics teaching assistant at a secondary school in Cambridge during undergraduate studies.

2014 English Language Teacher, Jinju Health College, South Korea

- Planned and led English lessons (30 hours p.w.) for a class of Korean students.
- Achieved highest test average (82%) among all 'advanced' classes.

- Provided personal academic and pastoral support outside of teaching hours.

OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCE		
Research Nov 2021	Visiting Researcher, Department of Statistics, Boston University	
	- Research visit funded by The Doris Chen Mobility Fund.	
May - Aug 2021	Quantum Machine Learning Scientist, Cambridge Quantum Computing	
	- Research on new methods for mitigating exponentially vanishing gradients ('barren plateaus') in Quantum Neural Networks.	
	- Supervised by Marcello Benedetti and Mattia Fiorentini.	
	Supervised of Literoons Denouted and Literoon I for the literoon of the litero	
Miscellaneous .		
2019 - 2021	Academic Editor, AsiaEdit	
	- Edited academic papers, articles, and grant proposals relating to Machine Learning and Statistics.	
2018 - 2021	Statistics Postgraduate Student Representative, Imperial College London.	
	- Represented views of students in academic & pastoral matters; organised social activities for staff and students.	
2015	Investment Banking Summer Analyst, Lazard	
	- Prepared pitch-book materials for client meetings, including financial analysis, market research, valuation models, and due diligence.	
ACADEMIC S	ERVICE	
Conference & V	Workshop Organisation	
Mar 2022	Workshop Co-Organiser. Heilbronn Institute of Mathematical Research: Internal Workshop.	
May 2021	Conference Co-Organiser. 4th Annual MPE CDT Symposium on Wellbeing,	
J	Inclusivity, Diversity and Equality in STEM (Virtual)	
Peer Review .		
2022 - present	Reviewer. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society (Series B: Methodology)	
2022 - present	Reviewer. Annales de l'Institut Henri Poincaré.	
2021 - present	Reviewer. Bernoulli.	
OTHER RELE	VANT SKILLS	
Computing	Programming Languages. Python (advanced), R (advanced), MATLAB	
	(proficient), C (proficient).	
	Programming Packages. PyTorch (advanced), Jax (advanced), TensorFlow	
	(proficient).	
	$ \textbf{Document Markup Languages. L} \textbf{a} \textbf{TeX} \ (\textbf{advanced}), \ \textbf{HTML} \ (\textbf{basic}). $	
	Version Control Software. Git.	